Hello, welcome everyone. This is active
inference guest stream number 121.1
on September 23rd, 2025.
We're with Mike Waste who will be
presenting and then discussing or O on
neuronal MTS is the quantum substrate of
conscious
active inference. So Mike, thank you for
joining. Looking forward to your
presentation and to the questions people
write in the live chat. So take it away,
please. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Daniel. Okay, so um yeah,
here's my title. What I'm going to try
and convince you of is uh so orc here
stands for orchestrated objective
reduction. I'll explain what I'm talking
about there. And MTS are the
microtubules.
And so, um, here's an outline.
Uh, oh, there we go. Here's an outline
of what I want to talk about. Um, the
second part here is the active inference
proposal. But I want to start by talking
about some evidence to make it plausible
to you that microtubules may be the
quantum substrate of consciousness. Um
before I go on to the specific active
inference proposal,
um I'm going to mention I don't think
we'll have time to talk about this, but
there's
another paper I I published recently
which addresses some of the more famous
conceptual problems with regard to
consciousness. I'm not sure if we'll get
to those, but I'm happy to talk about
those if we have time. But I figured for
this uh venue we want to focus on the
active inference side of the story. And
so before I start getting
diving into these details of
experimental evidence I want to talk
about, let me just summarize the overall
proposal we're making with regard to
active inference that I'm going to be
building up to so that you don't lose
the thread of what I'm trying to say. So
this uh this is our um graphical
abstract
where I've kind of got two uh columns
here or and three rows. At the top is
the most abstract level the theory of
active inference that describes optimal
behavior or an agent in a ma this
mathematical formalism.
There is a coarse functional mapping of
that theory onto parts of the brain
including
details like specific neurom modulators
having specific functional um roles in
the active inference theory. So that
match between neurohysiology and
neuroanatomy and the theory supports
that real brains do
use active inference.
Um but then the bottom part is is about
the implementation. Uh so so far most
active or all active inference process
models which attempt to say how neurons
might might might
implement active inference. Um,
this X at the bottom of the picture
there by the classical neural
implementation is meant to indicate that
it seems or at least it has not been
established that Hodgkin and Huxley
based classical models meaning uh
classical models that incorporate the
actual conductances that generate action
potentials in neurons have not
established that those kinds of neurons
those kinds of models can perform
perform the necessary sophisticated
mathematical operations
fast enough to implement active
inference
in real time for for like uh subsecond
decision making and inference and motor
control.
The other side is our proposal saying
that you know I want to emphasize that
I'm accepting active inference as at
least the first approximation a good
description of what the brain does. What
we're questioning is the implementation
of it in terms of classical neurons and
proposing instead that we have to
we have to uh resort to a quantum model
of how neurons work and in particular
taking into account quantum effects in
microtubules inside neurons.
So that's the overall proposal that
essentially microtubules are going to
implement conscious active inference.
But before I come to the active
inference part of the story, I want to I
want to convince you that there is at
least evidence there's uh that
microtubules may be the substrate of
quantum consciousness. And I'll start
with a um from the point of view of how
anesthetics
render us reversibly unconscious
and a bit of experimental evidence from
my lab. But so to to introduce this part
about anesthesia,
here's a quote from uh Claude Bernard,
one of the original investigators when
when we discovered anesthetics. And he
made this bold connect conjecture. He
said, "What is alive must sense and can
be anesthetized. The rest is dead." And
so for him, the ability be to be
anesthetized was almost a definition of
life itself. And he was basing that on
the fact that the same anesthetic gases
we're talk I'm focusing on volatile
anesthetics. Now, the same anesthetic
gases that render us and other
uh mammals reversibly unconscious
also
reversibly slow movement or stop
movement in invertebrates,
single-sellled organisms with no
neurons, and even plants.
So this uh chart I've got up here is a
uh table from a recent review of
mechanisms, potential molecular targets
of these volatile anesthetics. And you
can see people have many candidates uh
targets. Um in neuroscience, people tend
to focus on ion channels and
neurotransmitter receptors because those
are what govern the electrical activity
of neurons. But um there are other
potential targets and I'm going to focus
on the cytokeleletal elements known as
microtubules which we have in common
with everything else that is alive. Um
as well as ion channels are present in
in single cell organisms.
Okay. So moving forward um I want to
present this context that I'm comparing
two different
types of model of what consciousness
might be and how anesthetics might
reversibly render us unconscious. The
classical network uh picture is that um
it's a pattern of neuro of neural
activity ac across our brain distributed
across our brain and uh something about
when it is functionally integrated is
what makes us conscious.
Both these types types of models
emphasize functional integration over
raw neural activity as the neural
substrate of consciousness. Um but the
quantum picture suggests that the
substrate is act of consciousness is
actually the physical substrate of
consciousness is actually a physical
state of oscilly state of electric
dipoles in microtubules inside neurons.
I'm going to tell you a little more
about microtubules if they're not so
familiar. Um, but these are the two
types of models that we're comparing as
we look at the evidence about um how
anesthetics work. So
um because anes these volatile
anesthetics bind to many different pro
proteins in the body contemporary
contemporary researchers tend to assume
that they work by acting on some
combination of multiple targets. However
there are some classical results that
suggest instead that they might act
primarily on one main target. And uh
this uh first panel here at panel A is
showing the so-called Meer Overton
correlation
um between solubility and olive oil and
the how much of that molecule you need
to render someone or an animal
unconscious.
The solubility in olive olive oil um we
we understand in terms of a um
hydrophobic binding a lipophilic kind of
binding. So people think that these or
we know that these molecules bind into
uh lipohilic or hydrophobic pockets
inside many different proteins. Um but
this the reason that this correlation
suggests a one primary or so-called
unitary molecular target
is that all these molecules that you see
in the chart are diverse chemically.
Some of them are even just single atoms
elements. Xenon and nitrogen are
anesthetics at at sufficient
concentration. And so the fact that
these are chemically diverse but having
uh similar functional effects suggests
that they are operating not by a
chemical lock and key key and lock kind
of specific binding but some more
non-specific physical interaction like
Vanderwal's interactions among protein
dipoles.
So that's thing one on this slide. Panel
two or panel B here is showing another
fact that suggests
um it may not be many targets that are
relevant but one main one. And what
panel B is showing is the additivity
approximate additivity of doses of
different
um anesthetics. So that half of a dose
of benzene plus half of a dose of
cyclopropene adds up to about one full
dose. And these pairs on this chart are
chosen for having different effects on
particular ion channels like I think
isofllorane here has uh interacts
strongly with GABA receptors the
inhibitory receptors in the brain uh but
cyclopropane does not but nevertheless
when you add half of a dose of
cyclopropane to a half a dose of
isofllorine you get a full dose. So
these kind of data argue against the
combination
idea uh of how anesthetics work. And in
fact, well, yeah, I'll leave it there
for now. Um so in terms of what could
this one primary molecular target be,
you know, I'm going to say microtubules.
And we have a a strong theory
theoretical basis for saying that from
this um
quantum chemical simulation study which
essentially reproduced
a uh correlation like this about the
binding uh in terms of how well the diff
about seven of these anesthetics bind to
particular spots on microtubules and
disrupt
oscillation.
in those microtubules. Tubulin here are
the subunits that make up microtubules.
And so this theoretical study
essentially reproduces a Meer Overton
correlation, predicts which molecules
are going to be anesthetics and which
ones are not by
how well they disrupt these oscillations
in tubulin.
So uh that cannot be said for any other
candidate molecular
target of these volatile anesthetics. So
maybe microtubules really are the
relevant functional target. So quickly
what are they? Um they're they are
literally tubes uh inside all cells uh
not just neurons but in neurons they um
well and so in a biology class you first
learn that they they're called part of
the cytokeleton because they're stiff
and they act somewhat like bones. Um but
it is a stereotype to think of them as
purely structural because they have many
functional roles in single cells and in
neurons. And in neurons they have
special uh organizations and accessory
proteins that are different in the axon
and the dendrites.
And I have this one slide just to stand
for the general message that they are
not just tent poles in there or railroad
tracks. They are participating in all
kinds of dynamic
information processing and coordination
of movement. So in this beautiful dance
of the chromosomes during mitosis, it's
microtubules that are choreographing
that dance uh and actually pulling
things apart doing the movements. And in
single cells they are responsible for
swimming or uh so
this is there's a large literature about
these kinds of phenomena that I'm not
going to go into but I just am this is
to plant the idea in your head that we
already know that microtubules are not
just tent poles or railroad tracks in
okay so now coming to uh my
modest experimental contribution to this
story. We wanted to test whether
microtubules were are a functional
target of uh anesthetics in this case um
isofllorane anesthesia that's used in
people as well as in animals and we
found so um this drug epoylone B is a
drug that binds to microtubules and that
gets into the brain a brain penetrant
microtubial binding drug uh unlike many
of the other microtubial binding drugs
that are out there. And when we gave
that to our rats, the simple result was
they were somewhat resistant to uh
isofllorane anesthesia
as measured by how long it took them to
fall unconscious. And so we used uh
latency to loss of writing reflex as our
as our proxy for time to fall
unconscious. that the the writing reflex
is if you tip them on their back, if
they're awake, they will flip themselves
back over. And so when they don't flip
themselves back over, that's how you
know when they're unconscious. Um, and
so here's uh our results showing uh a
actually a large effect size uh 69
seconds longer to fall asleep with that
microtubial binding drug than without
it.
So um this by itself does not at all
mean that microtubules are doing
anything quantum. So we can consider how
might
microtubules contribute to to anesthesia
under these two different kinds of
pictures. And so under the classical
picture um one of the important
functions of uh microtubules in neurons
is as train tracks for the cute little
monkey munchkins that carry synaptic
vesicles and other packages to where
they need to go inside the neuron. So
perhaps um anesthetics disrupt that uh
fast axonal transport which could
plausibly lead to synaptic malfunction,
reduce activity levels and reduce uh
functional integration which under the
classical picture is necessary for
consciousness. Um however that doesn't
seem to be supported by what we know so
far. So there are a couple studies
showing that isofllorane does affect
synaptic transmission but those studies
looked at the mechanis molecular
mechanisms by which it did and they did
not involve microtubules. Uh in one case
it involved mitochondria instead.
So at present that picture doesn't seem
supported and any in any case one might
doubt if it would be a fast enough
mechanism to account for falling
unconscious in a few minutes. Um
before I go on to to the quantum point
of view, let me mention this uh cool
result in tadpoles showing that um
they engineered a a drug that's not one
of these volatile um anesthetics to mess
with microtubules and and they were able
to reversibly stop their tadpole from
swimming around. So this is evidence
consistent with the idea that um
anesthetics might be acting on
microtubules and microtubules might be
the substrate of consciousness. So here
is the abstract from uh my rat paper
that I was just talking about. I'm not
going to read it but just focus on this
last sentence. This finding
uh is predicted by models that posit
consciousness as a property of a quantum
physical state of neural microtubules.
So
I want to take a moment to say what the
motivation for this quantum point of
view is um because it's often ridiculed
as uh explaining one mysterious thing
with another mysterious thing. No, the
motivation for the quantum view of
consciousness is that a quantum model is
going to solve a fundamental problem
that cannot be solved by a by a
classical model. And it's a problem that
you don't need jargon or math to
understand. It's known as the phenomenal
binding problem. Here's a way it's
expressed in a neuroscience textbook.
Exactly how the parallel streams of
sensory data are melded into or fused
into perception, images, and ideas
remains the holy grail of neuroscience.
And I like this Dolly painting as a way
of of illustrating that idea. Uh it's a
portrait of his wife where, you know,
she's made out of molecules, but somehow
uh we have these unified conscious
experiences. How do we explain that? And
here's how uh the famous American
psychologist William James expressed
this problem already in his uh book
around uh 1900 or 8 around 1900. He
said, "Take a sentence of a dozen words
and take 12 men and tell to each one
word. Then stand the men in a row or jam
them in a bunch and let each think of
his word
as intently as he will. Nowhere will
there be a consciousness of the whole
sentences." So if each one is thinking
of a word, there's no sentence there. Um
his point was this applies to neurons
just as much as to people standing next
to each other and the neurons are not
even touching each other. There's a
synaptic gap between them. So how are
how do we form these unified holistic
conscious experiences?
That is what I'm saying a quantum model
can do because quantum physics is all
about irreducible holes wh
like we experience and there are no
irreducible holes in classical physics.
I'll pause in a moment, but let me
say the proposal. The the the proposal
is that a quantum substrate of
consciousness will provide that
irreducible unity to account for the
unity of consciousness and for its
physical efficacy. Uh uh we can talk
about that more if you like. Um but so
here's the the hammer off and Penrose
hypothesis.
Um,
I'll go fast about this review of
quantum physics. We know it. There's two
parts to a quantum evolution. The lo the
local and deterministic part and then a
measurement where you find out what
happens until then your wave function
only describes probabilities of
measurement outcomes.
And people often emphasize the
non-deterministic
nature of this. But what I want to
emphasize is quantum physics is
irreducibly holistic
uh and involves non-local correlations
that have been and what I like to refer
to as non-local coordination which has
been experimentally verified at large
macroscopic distances of kilometers and
resulted in Nobel prize in 2022.
So just uh illustrating the idea of wave
function collapse and pointing out it's
essentially a synonym for quantum state
reduction
when the distribution of possibilities
we say collapses and one of those is
actualized.
So um quantum physics has a measurement
problem.
It doesn't say what a measurement is or
what causes the wave function to
collapse or when it should collapse. Um,
objective reduction is a theoretical
point of view that says collapse is real
objective, not just epistemic. Okay, so
it's a real physical process. And
um Schroinger's cat is a fable to say
that quantum theory without if you try
to leave out the measurements that's
ridiculous because then you should be
you the theory predicts that there will
be half dead cats and those are not
observed. So this story that people
always talk about is to say you can't
leave out the measurements.
Um so uh here's orchestrated objective
reduction. So objective reduction
against again against refers to a theory
in which the collapse of the wave
function is a real physical process and
the orchestrated here is referring to in
biology in animals.
this
objective reduction has been
orchestrated so that it
corresponds to uh our our behavioral
problems that we have to solve and helps
us to solve them helps to perceive the
outside world and so on. So uh I'm
saying
or o associates quantum collapse events
in non-living matter with moments of
so-called protoconciousness. It's not
until you organize
larger chunks of matter like in a brain
using microtubules and neurons to
orchestrate those that you get something
like our what we call consciousness
rather than the protoconciousness.
Okay. So far I haven't showed you
much or any evidence for the quantum
part of the story. Here's Hammeroff and
Penrose. The infamous Hammer and
Penrose. Penrose. Everyone thinks he's a
genius, but nobody believes anything he
says. What's up with that?
Um, okay. So, now I'm gonna get to some
experimental
evidence.
Um, that microtubules can support
quantum effects at room temperature here
in this paper. Um,
let me step back to say the reason this
this uh this proposal has been around
for 30 years, the reason people have uh
considered it highly implausible and in
fact ridiculed it habitually is that it
was uh when we technologically try to
engineer quantum effects um it seems so
far that we need things to be super
cold. And so people thought the brain is
just too hot to support quantum effects
uh functional quantum effects,
functionally relevant quantum effects or
macroscopic quantum effects. Uh but now
we have direct bioysical evidence um in
microtubules in in vitro
uh showing this phenomenon called
quantum phenomenon called super
radiance. It's it's analogous to lazing
in a laser.
um it's at room temperature again and
moreover the effect gets stronger. Um
that's what this this plot that's hard
to read here is showing. The x-axis is
numb number of tryptophan residues. And
so you can re think of that as
essentially the size of the structure
that you're making out of your
microtubule.
is the the basic result on on this slide
is that the quantum effect gets stronger
as you make the microtubules into bigger
structures which is the opposite of the
usual prejudice which says that things
as they get bigger they get less
quantum.
So so far I've I've I've shown evidence
that uh microtubules can exhibit a
quantum effect a collective quantum
effect at room temperature. Maybe it
could happen at body temperature too. Um
now this next slide is just to represent
a whole bunch or a whole bunch of
experiments and a series of papers from
an Anerbond Bondopadier's lab
showing that so he's measured
microtubial high frequency microtubial
resonances
and he's able to stimulate them as well
and show that they predict and control
spiking activity.
Um so this is just a schematic to show
he's uh measuring from multiple neurons
in a dish. Now um and so without going
into details here um the the results I
want to take are a that microtubules
interact with membrane voltage and
spiking activity
and critically also their effects span
multiple neurons which is going to be
critical if this is going to be the
basis of a solution for the binding
problem which is how do we unify neural
activities that are happening
centimeters apart in the brain. Okay.
So, um
I take this to be important experimental
work that not many people have heard
about.
Um and finally uh for this part about
experimental evidence. So here is
evidence of a role for microtubules in
living neurons.
And here is one of a series of papers
showing
an entangled quantum state in the alive
human brain.
This made a little splash when it came
out, but I don't hear people arguing
about it anymore. They're just ignoring
it. Um, so these these uh researchers
just uh used a standard MRI machine but
dialed it to look for a different kind
of signal that they argued would be a
signal representing quantum
entanglement.
They recorded a signal with their MRI
machine that looked like an EMG of the
heartbeat, which they argued should not
be classically observable with an MRI
machine.
Um,
they saw the fidelity of this putitive
entanglement signal in the human brain
correlate with being awake versus asleep
when one of their subjects fell asleep
in their scanner. And they also
correlated it with working memory
performance in a different paper. So
that's direct biohysical evidence that
we have a macroscopic entangled quantum
state in our brain and it's actually
related to uh our conscious function. Um
in terms of people disbelieving this
there is one paper uh by one author who
says he doesn't believe it but he
doesn't provide any alternative
mechanism classical mechanism to explain
the signal that they observed. Here's
a good place to pause and see if there
are questions or clarifications,
objections.
>> Sure. I'll I'll read one question from
the live chat and then this is awesome.
>> So, Alex Sabine wrote, "Do the 12 people
and the sentence integration gestalt of
the sentence relate to the blind man and
the elephant? how
um
it's a little different from the blind
man and the elephant. So the blind man
and the elephant is about how different
people are getting different aspects of
the reality and none of them see the
full picture. this uh example with the
12 men and the sentence. Think of the
men as being as representing neurons and
if each neuron represents one feature or
word. Let's let's let's uh change the
example from a sentence to just seeing a
an orange chair. The color orange may be
represented by neurons in one place in
the brain where the shape of the chair
might be represented by neurons in
another part of the brain. So we can
imagine two men standing in next to each
other or two neurons. One of them
thinking orange and one of them thinking
chair shape
that does not add up to somebody having
a thought of an orange chair or a
perception of an orange chair. That's
what that example with the men thinking
of a sentence is meant to illustrate the
binding problem.
That also reminds me of the Daniel
Dennit thought experiment sequence that
starts with the brain and separates it
and continues to separate it and lump
and split different components and get
exactly at that which is kind of like
but even this thought example of the 12
people but but already it's presupposed
that each of them have an a unity. So
then how do we how do we um approach
that challenge of compositionality and
and um unity and and multicmposition
systems?
>> Yes. So um this issue is um I talk about
in more detail in that other paper I
mentioned. I'll just flash it up here.
this one um where I describe how
entanglement
quantum entanglement is
the structure of that unity. So the
entanglement among different parts of
the brain which I'm hypothesizing if
that can happen that provides a physical
basis for which things are unified and
which are not. So in the Denned
experiment, if you start taking out or
separating this neuron and that neuron
or that brain area and that brain area,
if they are no longer able to be quantum
entangled, that's when this picture
would predict you lose the unity of
consciousness. So we don't have to it
doesn't get all fuzzy and philosophical.
We can we have a physical basis for that
unity of consciousness under this
picture.
Awesome. Carry on.
>> Okay. So, I presented basically three
lines of three or four lines with the uh
anesthesia story of evidence,
experimental evidence for microtubules
and for quantum effects in microtubules
related to consciousness.
Um, I'm just going to mention here
there's a large literature that maybe
people are not aware of about so-called
quantum cognition
where people's answers to questions or
judgments about things can appear
irrational from a certain perspective.
Um there are so-called question order
effects and logical fallacies that can
be explained if you
do a quantumlike model of of human
cognition.
That in itself doesn't mean the
substrate has to be quantum. Um and the
this literature is largely agnostic
about that or probably assumes it is
class has a classical basis. But there's
a question uh no one has shown you can
get those kinds of effect from a
classical model yet. Um so I'm just
pointing to that set of issues and that
literature without a lot of discussion
right now.
And now um to to make the transition to
the
um active entrance part of the story, I
want to mention a paper by Fields at all
including Fristen uh Carl Fristen and um
uh Michael Leaven
where they essentially derived that
active inference and biology must be
quantum physical. I don't see people
talking about that paper for some
reason. I maybe I get the impression
that the first author Chris Fields is
the only one who believes it and the
other authors are just on there. I'm not
sure. Maybe maybe your viewers know more
about that than I do. Um but so now I'm
going to come to the active inference
part of the story and uh suggest that
among other things this ORC O
orchestrated objective uh reduction in
microtubules can account for discrete
cycles of perception and can implement
active inference.
Okay.
Um, so here's a little bit of an
expanded uh outline for the active
inference part. I guess I will skim
the introduction to active inference,
but you can tell me if if I should slow
down for that. Uh, but I'm assuming a
lot of this audience has heard about
that before. uh but then I'll spend a
little time talking about
ways um that it seems implausible that
classical neurons classical neural
models can actually implement active
inference fast enough for real time
subsecond inference and then I'll talk
about how orc o can solve so some of
those problems potentially
okay so um I want to approach this um
act of inference
with this quote um
referring to a quiet paradigm shift. You
know, in the last century, we had our
Hodgekin and Huxley model, deterministic
Hodgegkin, Huxley model of how neurons
work. And then we had this quiet
paradigm shift from that kind of
deterministic signal processing to
probabilistic inference uh and active
inference, which is an outgrowth of
that. Um, and I'm going to raise some
questions about
whether that works or not. Um, so, so
there's, in other words, there's a
tension between the determinist of
weights that we think neurons work
according to the Hodgekin Huxley model
and the stochasticity that you need to
assume
uh,
in active inference. And uh when I say
that I'm I I'm aware that the primary
kinds of active inference models are
deterministic as well. Uh but I I'll
clarify that in a minute. But so um
under active inference or probabilistic
coding in general,
our beliefs are represented by
probability distributions that represent
probabilities of different states of
affairs being true, probabilities of
different facts and um
and we update those beliefs by sensory
observations. And so here is BA's
rule way of expressing this updating
procedure where you have a prior belief
about states of the world s
um and that is compared to some
observations
to generate an updated or so-called
posterior belief based on the mismatch
between or so-called prediction error.
the mismatch between your prediction and
the observation. And these um
the diagrams here are illustrating how
this could be mapped onto neural
anatomy. If I just focus on the panel B
here, um it's showing three layers of
cortex where um the primary
input from the phalamus that you can
think of as sensory input comes into
layer four where those cells get sensory
inputs on the purple lines and they get
predictions from the black lines. And so
if those red cells can compare the
predictions to the observations,
that's how roughly we are imagining
neurons
computing prediction errors, the
difference between what you thought was
the case and what you observed. Um that
that are going to be used to update your
beliefs, which again are these
probability distributions saying how
likely different things are to be true.
Okay, so that was a general description
of uh predictive processing as it's
called or predictive coding
inference generalizes that picture to
include the agents behavioral response
among the states of the world that the
your probability distributions are
modeling.
Um, and this picture shows a mapping of
different variables in the active
inference theory onto parts of the
brain. I won't dwell on this, but
there's an impressive match between
variables in the theory and anatomy and
also neurohysiology. Uh, real neural
responses and pathological responses can
be accounted for. Uh, all sorts of
things can be accounted for.
uh behaviorally and neurally with this
theory. So it does so I want to
emphasize that it's not this theory that
I'm questioning. It's the classical
implementation.
Okay. Given this uh
normative theory or abstract
algorithm about how an agent should um
behave or should infer
perceptions or or states of the world to
be optimal. Um we can consider how could
we get neurons to do that. And there's
basically two broad strategies. I won't
go into too much detail but just make
you aware um that there's a a stream of
the literature where they where neural
activities rep represent expected values
like means and variances of the
probability distributions that we're
trying to represent.
And the alternative formulation is
neural activities are just sampling
each time they fire or at each moment
they're sampling
stochastically randomly from
that that probability distribution that
represents your beliefs. uh rather than
representing it in terms of uh you know
parameters of a of a parameterizable
distribution like a Gaussian.
Um okay and there are pros and cons to
these that I I'll skip for now. Um now
this this inference
cycle that I outlined with this baze
rule here is intractable for most real
parameters in our model in our beliefs
to optimize our beliefs.
Okay. So that's our first approximation.
uh before going on to more about the
computations that you need in to
implement active inference, let me say
how I'm thinking of consciousness and I
didn't make up this way of of defining
consciousness, but um
got it from the literature, but there
are a few different ways that people in
the active inference literature think of
consciousness.
Um one is in terms of boundary
representations.
I won't try to describe what those are
because I'm not going to use I'm not
going to use that definition or this
mid-level hierarchical re
representations might be postulated to
be the conscious ones. Instead,
whoops. Instead, I'm going to use this
third concept um which is the most
intuitive one I think and uh was
endorsed by Carl Fristen in at least one
paper. But so the idea here is conscious
agents as distinct from uh reflex acting
agents or unconscious agents are ones
that have what they call counterfactual
or temporal depth.
And that's really just equivalent to a
fast implicit planning function.
Before each moment of consciousness,
um the agent needs to integrate over a
bunch of possible interpretations
and possible plans for what to do next
um to come up with the optimal
inference and perception and next
action. And so that corresponds to this
counterfactual word here is referring to
considering things that might happen
that haven't happened that aren't that
fictitious
uh things that you might do in the
future. And temporal depth here is
referring to how much into the future
you're implicitly considering before
making your inference or your decision.
Uh so that's my operational definition
of consciousness in the context of
active inference.
So I'm going to talk about what a
agent with temporal depth needs what
computations it needs to be able to do
according to active inference. First I
want to point out uh briefly and then
I'll come back to this later that
although we hear it formulated in terms
of the free energy principle that
formulation is equivalent to a
formulation in terms of least action the
least action principle and under that
formulation you
describe the uh the inference cycle in
terms of a path integral which is just
doing what I basically the implicit
planning function that I just described
intuitively here. X0 is some state at
some initial state and XT is your state
or position some later time and the
paths are all the different trajectories
actions you could take in between to get
to that later state.
Um
uh act of inference is equivalent or
conscious or sentient act of inference
is equivalent to implicitly considering
possible
uh futures to decide on an optimal one.
And again this is not me making this up.
This is in the textbook and the
literature. It's well established. But I
also show it in the paper that uh the
pair of papers that we're talking about.
Okay. So now coming to some some of the
things that you need to compute.
Well, maybe I'll pause a moment to see
if if that was too fast about active
inference.
>> Nope. Great. Continue.
>> Okay.
Okay. So, we're taking active inference
for granted. Um see if I can make you
see my face. Um but I'm I'm questioning
a classical implementation and so I'm
going to focus on a few few points
listed here. Um but first let me
introduce the computations that we need.
Um so I already mentioned this first
approximation
uh in the top line there and uh this
green row E refers to another
approximation that I'm going to mention
later. I've got a bunch of different
computations that are needed to do the
path integral. Um, but I'm just going to
focus on the need for linear sums,
linear combinations of firing rates of
different neurons
that you need to do that pathog
integral. An integral is a sum.
um I'm going to focus on that operation
and the uh stochasticity or randomness
in the neurodynamics that is also
necessary. Um and then after that I'll
talk about that problem of discrete
perceptual moments that I uh mentioned
earlier.
Okay. So here is an example of an active
inference process theory. again what
they mean by process theories are
hypothetical mappings onto neural uh
onto neurons. Um and so I'm just uh
highlighting here down at the bottom
that what I said before is in the
literature, not just me saying it. This
it's equivalent to following Hamilton's
principle of least action or path
integral. But anyway, the neural models
that they use are idealized.
um
they are firing rate models that don't
include spikes. Some of them do include
spikes but not by modeling the actual
conductances that generate the spikes
just as with random number generators.
So firing another idealization is that
firing rates are interpreted as
probabilities because remember we're
trying to use these neurons to represent
probability distributions.
And in the theory, I didn't show this,
but in the equations of the theory, we
need to consider logarithms of
probabilities as well. And so to get
neurons to do that, they assume that
postsaptic potentials are proportional
to logarithms of probabilities and
firing rates are proportional to raw
probabilities.
They have an idealized function to
translate those potentials into firing
rates. They assume they can add that
different neurons can add their firing
rates linearly
and they assume that uh conscious
inferences happen every cycle of a
so-called uh theta rhythm in the brain
but they do it by hand in the model
without any mechanistic model of how
neurons might do that.
So um I'm going to consider now just
because these are idealizations or
approxim approximations doesn't mean
they're wrong but I'm going to I'm going
to point out that they are not
established as being right and it's
somewhat implausible that they are uh
right that they will uh are sufficient
uh to do these computations
um in fast time scales subsecond time
scales for real time control. So, um, a
problem I didn't mention on the outline,
but it relates to adding together
different possibilities of what might
happen or what you might be seeing. Um,
this is from a uh process model
describing a simple behavioral task
using active inference to describe uh to
make a proc a neural process model of a
simple behavioral task in a rat. and it
had four positions of a uh behavioral
target and four spatial positions the
rat could go in. And that meant they
needed a separate neural population for
each combinations of all the different
factors that are involved in the
environment the agent is trying to
represent. In this case, it was 16.
But this points to a potential
combinatorial explosion if you need
different populations of neurons to
represent every possible combination of
things that might be out there and
things that you might do.
Okay. So coming back to this quote to
highlight the tension potential tension
between the deterministic
signal processing point of view and the
new probabilistic point of view. The
question is how do deterministic
Hodgekin and Huxley neurons do
probabilistic inference?
So I'm not putting up these equations.
The this is the Hodgekin and Huxley
equations. I'm not putting them up to go
into details about what they're saying
except to show they're all deterministic
differential equations. There's no
random numbers over here.
This is a purely deterministic evolution
over here. We've got a probabilistic
algorithm.
How do you get deterministic neurons to
do classical neurons to do that? Well,
um,
one of, so I said one of the
operations we have to be able to do is
to add, um, neural activities linearly.
And so here's, uh, a paper from 2006
where they modeled neurons to see if
they could get linear summation,
the straight line in this plot. And in
order to get that to achieve robust
linearity with these integrating fire
neurons, they had to average over more
than a thousand neurons and more than a
thousand trials.
And to get some randomness, they had to
assume randomness in the in the inputs.
So
my point in showing this is that if you
imagine how many neurons would it take
to get robust linear summation like this
in one trial
which we need in order to be able to use
active inference in real time. You it
seems
heruristically we would need a million
neurons.
too many. That that's that's on the
order of how many should be able to
represent a whole range of different
features, not just one
linear combination pertaining to one of
those features. Um, so this is to say it
appears to take too long and this model
is not even a realistic Hodgekin and
Huxleybased model that incorporates the
real basis of the spikes.
But the field of active inference seems
to be relying on this paper and maybe
one or two other models like this to
establish that classical neurons could
do these these operations.
So the other issue I said I was going to
uh focus on a bit is the issue of neural
variability. Um real neurons
exhibit stochasticity or randomness
variability in their firing from trial
to trial. Even if you give them
identical stimuli,
um
the
variability in stimuli oops the input
variability does not account for the
neural variability and neither does the
known randomness at at uh synapses.
I'm sorry I don't have the references
for that up here, but they're in our
papers. Um so from the remember I said
there were two approaches to uh
representing um probability
distributions in active inference. the
deterministic version. Well, they need
to somehow get this randomness or
stochasticity into their model to match
real to real neurons as we record them
in real behaving animals and people
because it's not there in the
deterministic model. And on the flip
side, um the sampling approach assumes
stochasticity in their model. But if
Hodkin and Huxley neurons are presumed
to be underlying that model, where does
the stochasticity come from? Since that
model is deterministic and again the
stochasticity at synapses is not enough
to account for the stochasticity of real
neural activity.
So these are not to pro prove that a
classical implementation is impossible
but to say it has not been demonstrated
with neural models that incorporate the
known Hodkin and Huxley conductances
that are the basis of the action
potentials.
Um also I mentioned that this formalism
for a conscious agent is equivalent to a
path integral considering
uh perceptual interpretations and
behavioral responses.
That path integral is also intractable
computationally. And so another um
approximation is introduced into the
classical process models called the mean
field approximation where you assume
each of the time steps of each tra of
these hypothetical trajectories into the
future paths or policies of what you're
going to do in the future. You have to
assume that each time step into the
future is statistically independent of
the other time steps,
which is not really a good assumption
intuitively because our behavioral plans
should be coherent plans that are not
random choices at each moment during
that that behavior. So, this is not a
great thing that we're being forced to
do. um
but I'm mentioning it because the
quantum model will not need to make this
approximation.
So um
we already saw the need or there we
there there was already a need for
multiplication and addition because the
active inference equations have matrix
multiplication in them. This um mean
field approximation
implies more need for multiplication
because when you treat different factors
uh as independent you multiply their
probabilities to get the overall all
probability of some path or or
trajectory in the future. Um and so that
leads to a sort of catch 22. If your
neural activities, if you postulate that
your neural activities correspond to
probabilities, then maybe it's
relatively straightforward to add them.
But
uh multiplying them becomes non-trivial.
And the flip side, if you postulate that
neural activities correspond to
logarithms of probabilities, then you
just have to add them and that is
equivalent to multiplication. But then
if you you need need to add raw
probabilities that becomes non-trivial.
So it seems like whichever way you
choose you have to leave out something
that you need. And so the solution
that's been adopted in the the example
process model there is that maybe the
synaptic potentials are carrying are
representing the log probabilities and
the rates are the raw probabilities the
firing rates of neurons.
We have some experimental evidence. I
won't dwell on this experiment just just
showing that in the abstract they're
showing that neural activity in this
area lip of a monkey was consistent with
it's integrating
a variable that was proportional to a
log likelihood rat a log likelihood. In
other words, a log probability. So
there's some experimental evidence that
neurons do compute log probabilities.
But that's not equivalent to a classical
model that shows how a classical
Hodgekin Hxley neuron can do it. We to
my knowledge we do not have such a
model.
Similarly, um these models tend to
almost universally re rely on
convergence into attractor states which
are quasistable
patterns of activity. Um and that
represent different possibilities. Um,
and this has been critic criticized by
people other than us because when we're
talking about fast real time inference
as opposed to learning on longer time
scales for fast real-time inference,
attractors might be too slow because um
different areas have different
conduction delays from the eyes or the
ears to the cortex uh to the visual or
auditory cortex.
um and sensory inputs are changing from
moment to moment. So it's not so easy
potentially to get a quasi stable
pattern of activity going and the
there's a question about how long do you
have to keep it going in order for it to
register or as that's the answer.
Um so that's a another doubt about
whether uh classical models can account
for these computations. So here's a
summary of that that um
critique of the classical
implementations. And in the title there
I should have been more specific than
realistic. I mean by realistic I mean a
classical model that incorporates the
Hodgekin and Huxley conductances that
are responsible for action potentials.
So what these models, these classical
process models have not established is
that h they have not established that um
Hodkin and Hxley neurons can quickly add
their firing rates linearly
in like 200 milliseconds. the fluent
alternation that I was talking about.
Whoops. Between
uh multiplication and summation that is
necessary for matrix multiplication not
been demonstrated. The log
some variables are logs of probabilities
and some are probabilities. How do you
do that with neurons? There's no I don't
know of a model that shows how to do
that with realistic neurons.
The papers that did show linear
summation with neurons s suggested it
would take too long or too many neurons
to get
addition to work right to do this in
under a second. Um
and here I me I mentioned there's a
problem accounting for the real
stochasticity or or variability in in
neurons
uh given a deterministic model.
So I next want to go to uh the quantum
picture. I guess I'll flash one more
thing before I pause to ask for
questions which is as a sort of segue to
the quantum proposal. Uh I mentioned
earlier this paper
um from 2022
based on these results at the bottom of
the abstract here we suggest that
biological systems employ quantum
coherence as a computational result as a
resource and implicitly as a
communication resource. And here is a
place where they are very t um sort of
cryptically saying they think
perception is quantum. One might imagine
that a combination of quantum computing
and neuromorphic engineering may be able
to account for real human vision.
The results obtained here suggest that
quantum biology is far as larger than we
thought so far and all biological
systems are quantum systems and use
quantum coherence as an information
processing resources. This has been
suggested before but here we showed that
it follows from general principles.
That's what I underlined at the bottom
there.
Sounds like a big deal, but I haven't
heard anybody else talking about it.
Um, okay. So, before I go on, uh, any
questions, clarifications, complaints?
>> There there are a few questions. I think
continue on and close out and then we'll
I'll read them in the discussion. Thank
you though.
>> Very good. Okay. Um, okay. So I talked
about some problems with particular
computations
and now let me introduce another issue
that any theory of conscious active
inference any process model has to
address which is that our moments of
experience are nonover overlapping
discrete moments like frames of a movie.
um and I don't this does not seem to be
largely known appreciated but it is well
established
um so the kinds of experimental evidence
that uh establish this are for example
the large psychophysical literature on
backward masking
so uh the bottom schematic there is
illustrating a trial like that where the
schematic is showing what subjects would
be looking at they're fixating on the
dot in the middle. The pair of bars here
of unequal length are flashed very
briefly and they're supposed to note
which one was longer and that's to test
whether they saw those bars or not. But
after th that target those target bars
are flashed very briefly. These
sideways equal signs are the masks that
are flashed briefly after the targets.
And if you flash them soon enough,
within a few hundred milliseconds of the
targets, you can prevent the targets
from being seen at all. And so a large
literature of effects like that appear
to prove that our brain integrates some
finite duration
of time to generate each of our moments
of perception.
And you know, you can reflect that if
that weren't true, we wouldn't be able
to perceive movement because movement we
perceive by noting something was in a
different place at two different times.
Um, so there are many there are a bunch
of other experiments that come to a
similar conclusion. I think I'll I won't
describe them now for time. Um but I
think the backward masking is is enough
to establish that um these cycles of
perception are nonover overlapping. So
it's not like a continuous update where
new sensory information kind of breaks
in whenever it gets whenever it's uh
observed. rather there you only get to
be noticed at these
discrete moments
and this is also a requirement in
conscious active inference.
I think there's a little bit of
confusion about this maybe in the
literature, but it's clear
that even when you go to a continuous
description of active inference using
differential equations,
you still need to supplement that with
if it's going to be a conscious uh
temporally deep agent, you need to
supplement that continuous instantaneous
description with something that
integrates over a finite window.
the temporal depth to generate the
sentient or conscious inference. So we
know in real life there are discrete
moments of experience and conscious
active inference requires discrete
moments of experience.
The question is how do you get neurons
to generate discrete moments of
experience? Um before I go to that
question, here's just another way of
seeing this result. We can see neural
coralates of these moments of our the
movie of our life during uh binocular
rivalry experiments where you show two
different pictures to the two eyes and
um instead of seeing a combination,
people alternate seeing one or the other
and the the stimulus is not changing.
Both eyes are still see are seeing the
same picture the whole time are being
shown the same picture the whole time
but your brain
decides what it's going to see at each
moment and it alternates
uh between the two pictures and what
this study this 2009 study showed with
EG
uh electrical recordings from the scalp
is um moments of neural synchronization
rhythmic moments of neural
synchronization
uh that correspond to these moments of
perceptual experience.
Okay. Um
so recall this was the ORC O hypothesis
and um here again is the statement of
the idea quantum collapse events is what
O refers to. It doesn't become
consciousness until the the objective
reduction events are orchestrated by
biological structures to be more
complicated and informative.
Now um coming back to the quant the path
integral formulation I want to emphasize
the distinction between the qu the path
integral formulation in quantum physics
and in classical physics. You can
formulate classical physics and active
inference in terms of the least action
principle
uh which is expressed in terms of this
path integral. But in classical physics
that's optional. It's redundant with the
instantaneous description in term
differential equation kind of uh
description. It's equivalent. the the
system just follows the path path of
least resistance. They say
the situation is different in
quantum physics. That's why I say here
it's mandatory. You can't get away with
an instantaneous differential
description.
um instead and I I want to
also say um this path integral
formulation of quantum physics is
the most fundamental formulation. Uh
things like the Schroinger the
non-relativistic Schroinger equation
that are introduced as postulates in
introductory courses can be derived from
the path integral formulation in the
non-relativistic limit. Though the
general description of quantum physics
is in terms of this path integral where
at each moment nature decides what it's
going to do next. What it's going to do
at the next quantum measurement
by considering every conceivable
trajectory the system could take in
between now and that future measurement.
It integrates over all those
possibilities
um without any approximation like we had
in the classical case the mean field
approximation.
Um
and in the quantum case it again this is
not equivalent to the instantaneous
description in terms of forces or
derivatives.
That's why I'm saying it's a mandatory
description. And so it's as if nature
considers everything that it could do
next at the next measurement event
and picks an optimal one based on
minimizing the action the physical
action. That's the least action
principle that I said is equivalent to
the free energy principle.
And that's why that's why our proposal
that orchestrated quantum objective
reduction could implement conscious
active inference is
is is founded on a rigorous equivalence
mathematical equivalence not a loose
analogy as one of our reviewers called
it.
Maybe I'll pause there because this is
the proposal before I flesh it out. This
is the proposal
if you want to clarify anything.
Indeed, that there's a
path that can be splined or interpolated
>> that's based upon the biological time
cycle and
cognitive or computational capacity and
frequency of actual mechanistic
processes that are known where necessity
and sufficiency and non-human models and
relevant human data exist
to to come together to provide a a
mechanistic how along with a kind of
full MAR levels of analysis or even more
of like a tinburgen style for questions
analysis. That's what theory integration
looks like in biology.
That's where it's at.
Okay. So yes, it on this slide I'm at
the algorithmic level
and I need to specify what is going to
implement it at the the bottom level,
the implementation level. Um, and I'm
saying uh microtubules can do that. Um,
but but this formalism applies to nature
at large in general. nature does this
and we're saying it does it in a
particular way in brains
um where it's been orchestrated so that
what is represented is something that's
useful to the organism. Here's just to
make it a little more concrete how I'm
picturing this happening in neurons. So
these are cartoon neurons where I've got
these fat dendrites with microtubules in
them. And here are some axons with
synaptic terminals. And I'm pointing out
there's a lot of actin in the synaptic
terminals and um
actin can exist in a liquid crystal
state which is used um as logic gates in
uh optical computers and we've got an a
quantum optical I'm hypothesizing a
quantum optical computer in the
microtubules. So the actin at the um at
the synapses could be acting as gates
that modulate synaptic release
probabilities based on the quantum state
in the uh microtubules.
And the m the quantum state in the
microtubules reflects neural activity on
the membrane because there are voltage
gated calcium channels all over the
neural dendrites and microtubules and
microtubial associated proteins are
sensitive to calcium.
And so that's how so
uh a critical requirement for this
hypothesis to be viable is that this
hypo this hypothetical quantum state in
the microtubules must be able to
communicate with action potentials on
the membrane
both ways because we know action
potentials is how our sensory inputs are
represented and we know action
potentials is how we act uh uh contract
muscles to behave. included in talking.
So the if this is true, the microtubules
have to be able to talk to the membrane
potential and the way we can imagine
that concretely is that the way the
membrane potential talks to the
microtubules is via calcium. The pattern
of intracellular calcium mirrors the
pattern of electrical activity across
the membrane. So it can imprint that
onto the microtubial oscilly state.
That's how the microtubules find out
what you're looking at. And now, how do
the microtubules modulate what you do in
response? By modulating synaptic release
probabilities at the uh axon terminals
where we know where in the central
nervous system uh synaptic vesicle
release is notoriously unreliable. They
say noisy and they speculate about why
would you want unreliable neurons? Well,
that provides a point where the
microtubial state can modulate the
neural activities without violating the
known Hodgekin and Huxley
dynamics that we know about.
>> So, it's interesting that that's also
called quantized release and it really
does come down to the to the discrete
packets of vesicles themselves with
discrete composition of of molecules and
neurotransmitters. That's true. That
could muddy the issue. I'm not claiming
that discrete packets, we do call them
quanta, but they are not quant in the
quantum physical sense necessarily. Uh
yeah, but yeah, it is it is kind of
funny that we use that word. Um
I think um yeah I want to emphasize uh
that this gives an advantage to beings
that can evolve such a conscious dynamic
whereas consciousness appears
epiphenomenal and useless in classical
models. um the capacity. So there's a
tendency to say quantum computation is
hyped, overhyped because, you know,
there's only a few um
quantum algorithms and they're mostly
useful if you're trying to rob a bank.
Um so maybe it's all hype, but speed is
not the only potential advantage of
quantum computation. Memory capacity is
another one. And this is a significant
issue for neuroscience because our
models of neuron of of memory are linear
models like the Hopfield model if you've
heard of that are their capacity how
many memories you can store is linear in
the number of neurons. So if 10 neurons
can store
two memories 100 neurons might only
store 20 memories and it goes up
linearly.
That's a severe constraint and there's a
question about whether that's enough to
account for our massive memory capacity
over decades and hundred years. In
contrast, by marrying the quantum
algorithm, search algorithm called
Grover's algorithm with a neural network
architecture,
uh these guys in 2000 came up with a
quantum associative memory whose
capacity was exponential in the number
of neural units. Since then there's been
develop further development of related
models where the advantage is polomial
or the u the capacity is polomial or
even exponentially better than the
classical models. So there's potentially
a huge
memory advantage if we're just looking
for bottom level. What would what would
it how would it help to have such a
quantum system to use in your brain?
potentially it can account for our
ability to remember things over a
hundred years and use single episodes
from decades ago in our momentary
inferences about what to do in
sub-second time scales.
Um
I I don't have a slide for it but I want
to briefly mention that there is also a
concrete model um by Beera and um
Elitzer in 2005 showing how you can
program
neurons.
It's basically a quantum process model.
You can program neurons
um
assuming a quantum state inside the
neurons which they don't speculate about
what it might do. But when they assume
that they get eyetracking behavior that
dramatically outperforms the classical
common filter type models and introduces
um discrete jumps in the eye movements
when when you're trying to follow a
moving target with your eyes that match
real qualitatively match real eye
tracking data but are not present in the
classical models. So that was back in
2005. I I don't specialize in that field
but I I'm not aware of any newer
developments or models superseding
those. So because the quantum
description is equivalent to the path
integral formulation as I tried to
emphasize earlier that quantum model is
an example of how you could neurally use
a quantum system for active inference
for a concrete behavior of tracking uh
something with your eyes. And so that
simple model could potentially be
generalized to more complex behaviors.
Okay, so there's that model illustrating
concretely how you could use this in a
brain. I'm saying there's also the
potential memory advantage of a quantum
model. And so given the experimental
evidence that I reviewed at the
beginning, that's why I say
quantum collapse on the microtubial
state inside of neurons is actually
experimentally supported. It's
consistent with what we know about
neurohysiology in a way that arguably
these classical models are not. Even
though I admit this is a speculative
model,
it it it is consistent with the
deterministic uh function uh Hodgekin
Huxley function of the neurons
and and mod doing the quantum modulation
through the stochastic synaptic release
uh as a potential example. Um
so um here I I'll wrap up now. This
table just um summarizes
different um issues for theories of
consciousness, a classical theory or
quantum theories. I've been emphasizing
issues around probabilistic optimization
and active inference
and this discrete decisions uh moments
issue.
Um, but I brought up the unity of
consciousness, the binding problem,
epifenomenalism. I didn't even mention a
effect. Whoops. Um, or non an arrow of
time, subjective arrow of time, but
these are some other issues where the
quantum model may have an advantage. So,
I'm just throwing those up there for
completeness.
So, I think to finish, I'll just put my
um outline. So you can point at stuff
that you would like to ask about or talk
about more.
>> Awesome.
Okay, there's a bunch of written
questions and anyone else can can write
some questions while I just compile them
and and uh
move into the discussion just maybe a
little bit. How did you come to work on
the empirical work and the the animal
biology and the theoretical biology and
and just how has that come to be that
way in 2025?
>> Yeah. Um well, I got interested in this
idea way back in the '9s when I was a
physics grad student, uh high energy
theory, elementary particle physicist.
So I got excited about these ideas and
uh got my foot in the door to
neuroscience through computational
neuroscience and then decided I needed
to learn to do experiments so I wouldn't
be begging experimentalists for their
data to analyze and I learned to do uh
multielerode recordings in behaving rats
um and my motivation there was interest
in the binding problem um to address
that from the main from a classical
neuroscientist ific point of view, you
want to be able to look at multiple
neurons at the same time and see how
they're coordinating in real time or
synchronizing.
Um but it's not till the past few years
that I've
managed to join the discussion about the
quantum hypothesis by I noticed that um
so these microtubial binding drugs
um have been known for a long time as
anti-cancer drugs because they interfere
with mitosis and cancer is runaway cell
division and that is governed by the
microtubules. So messing with the
microtubules
apparently helps to slow to slow down
cancer.
Um but most of those drugs as I
mentioned don't penetrate well into the
brain. Um but more recently I I came
across a review describing people
developing brain penetrant microtubial
stabilizing drugs to to go after brain
cancers. And that made me think maybe
that's an opportunity to test whether
anesthetics target microtubules.
>> Awesome. All right, I'm gonna ask a
bunch of questions that have been
written in the chat. They're they're all
over, but it should be fun and and
associative. All right, first your
colleague Ernesto Sores wrote,
>> oh,
>> is there an analogous phenomena for
qualia to the collapse of the wave
function? In other words, is the
collapse of some wave function in the
brain what makes us aware of Aqualia?
>> Yes. In in under the ORO theory,
we're equating moments of consciousness
with moments of orchestrated collapse.
And so the way I would phrase it to try
and be philosophically careful is the
consciousness, the conscious experience
is a property of that physical collapse
process.
And the collapse is when the irreducible
unity
or coordination or non-local
um
correlations manifest themselves. And so
that's how it can be the physical
objective basis to the unity of
consciousness that we experience.
>> Great transition to the next question
from Benjamin.
>> Good to hear from Ernesto.
>> Cool. There's more coming. Benjamin G
wrote, "If the Penrose Hammeroff or O
model is a helpful model, I wonder if
that increases the likelihood of the
Fuller Bone Penrose Hammeroff model and
other David Bowisms, not just
Penroseisms.
I have not heard of a Bone Penrose model
because I think the Bone model is not
consistent. is a different model that's
not consistent with orchestrated with
objective reduction. Now there are a
number of different theories of
objective reduction and Penrose has a
particular one um but the Bowian
interpretation or theory of quantum
physics
uh and my understanding does not have
actual collapse.
You just find out what happens. It still
has the non-locality though. So in that
respect it might still provide a basis
for binding. But in this picture, this
picture is
totally distinct from the bombian
picture.
>> Interesting. Yes, with the implicit
order and the pilot wave. Um, okay.
>> Right. Benjamin asks
my understanding is that tubulin and
microtubules are not only in human or
mammal neurons but eg are similarly
found in fungal hay and you know
editorial note all all cellular life. So
what are implications of this on fungal
computation?
Fungal um I am not prepared to talk
about fungi but I I have learned about
single-sellled organisms. I mean yeah
almost all life has microtubules. I
think there are some exceptions and even
they may have microtubial like proteins
but speaking broadly it's yeah cellular
life tends to have microtubules
um and in line with that I mean that's
related to my point earlier that
volatile anesthetics that reversibly
make us unconscious
have analogous effects at comparable
concentrations on single-sellled
parramia that swim around without any
neurons but they do have microtubules
and they use them to swim with. Um
so
this picture
I would say unlike the classical picture
that emphasize that is all about the
skin only of neurons or the membrane of
neurons only. This picture makes it
understandable how our consciousness is
continuous
with similar stuff earlier in biology.
you know, um, I don't know if a
parramium is conscious, but it appears
to be it's it's sensitive. I've done it
myself. I've anestthetized parramia with
isofllorane, and I'm trying to do the
same experiments that we did in rats on
tetraheimina and um, parramsia single
cells to implicate microtubules in uh,
the anesthetic effect on them. But um
what I'm suggesting is that
evolutionarily microtubules already had
a function of integrating sensory
information and coordinating movement.
We've just built on that.
>> Maybe also just
>> um there are micro tubule stabilizers
and destabilizers and you know different
mechanics of how they bind different
places etc. So
dissolving seems to remove their
function. But also you talked a lot
about microtubule stabilizing which I
know over longer time scales can
influence the pool of subunits and the
assembly dynamics even through the
stabilizing kinetics. But in the shorter
term is that what is being hypothesized
to matter or like is it about them being
obviously break again breaking them down
just dissolves the substrate. So that's
that's easy for loss of function on on
transport as well as any any other
features but does stabilizing remove the
function or does it modif you know what
what matters the phosphorilation state
just their their sheer assembly?
Yeah, thanks for asking that question.
Um and some new results have made me
question how I was thinking about this
but the way I was thinking about this
initially is not in ter
the stabilization I think was kind of a
I thought was a red herring that is um
our experiment was just showing that the
binding by this drug was maybe getting
in the way of the isofllorane and so
it's it's certainly not that we're
completely dissolving or deolymerizing
the microtubules maybe
well yeah so the drug is a stabilizer
um so maybe that could have interfered
with transport without actually breaking
them apart under a classical picture but
under the quantum picture it's
interfering with their collective
vibrations
um
okay but so the way I was interpreting
our result was simply that it took the
rats longer to fall asleep when we gave
them the microtubial drug because the
microtubial drug was getting in the way
of the isofllorine.
>> So kinetically blocking a a in a sort of
non in a way that there's also like GPCR
binding drugs or or molecules that will
sterically hinder a psychoactive. So
they'll reduce the effect of a ion
channel but not have a direct
phenomenological effect or even a a
kinetic effect. And so something similar
that that sterically hinders something
that would interfere
with reducing the the quantum action.
>> Right?
>> That's how I was interpreting it. But
since then I've seen some results. So
under that interpretation, you kind of
would expect that the more of the the
microtubial binding drug you would get
uh that you gave, the more resistance to
the anesthesia you would get. However,
um this is preliminary now, but I I I
saw a paper that did this in mice and
when they gave the drug for two weeks,
we just gave it one one time and looked
what happened the next couple days. when
they gave it for two weeks, they saw an
opposite effect where the mice were more
sensitive to anesthesia. And I think I
may have seen something like that in my
single cells too when I left them in the
microtubial drug for multiple days um
that they became more sensitive and
instead of less sensitive. So that's
making me question the just steric
blocking interpretation. And maybe it
does have to do with how stiff the
microtubules are and how well they
vibrate or something like that.
>> Um
story is getting interesting.
>> Yeah, there's there's a lot going on.
There's phosphorilation and there's uh
there's a lot going on down there. But
>> I don't think it's I I think it's more
of a direct or like the modeling study
and other uh considerations
lean me away from things like
phosphorilation
to just direct physical interactions
like Vanderwal's induced dipoles
interfering with the the dipole
oscillations directly. It
>> that's a detail,
>> you know, interesting. Of course, we're
just raising possibilities, but for for
years, I have seen that ideas that the
combinatorics of the phosphorilation
states
could also it's and and this kind of
relates to a uh one one question that
was in the chat of uh
Ernesto. What what about electrical
stimulation of the cortex which elicits
repeatable qualia? Does it really? But
do different areas of the brain become
transiently entangled? And then just one
one thought that I wrote in there was
seems like there could be multilateral
causality electromagnetic quantum
material changing one can change others.
So the ver the fact that there's
experiments where one is upstream
causally of another
when ultimately it's part of the same
causal nexus. Like if you were to
deplete nitrogen that would influence
microtubule dynamics over some time
frame. But that doesn't mean that
nitrogen plays a pro approximate
mechanistic role but so everything can
kind of re-enter the same causal nexus
and that's why it is important to do the
experimental work that you're
discussing.
>> Okay. So the question remind me the
question now again
>> um
>> what about electrical stimulation of the
cortex
>> electrical stimulation which elicits
qualia
>> okay I think before I comment on that I
wanted to you said um you mentioned the
microtubial associated proteins and how
they their states are changed by
phosphorilation and so on and so I think
it might be helpful for me to bring up
the metaphor of a guitar where the
microtubules are like the guitar strings
and you can imagine
microtubial associated proteins being
placed on like fingering different frets
and that's how you get different chords
playing which represent different
perceptions or experiences.
Um and that's how you could store them
as memories as well if you can hold on
to those frets for a long time. Um and
then the actual strumming I guess
stretching the metaphor a little bit is
the um the uh uh calcium coming in to
affect the the microtubial state and and
uh encode the neural activity state into
the microtubules. Um okay. So that was
just to relate to the microtubial
associated proteins and how they could
be involved in learning. For sure
there's there's evidence that they are
involved in learning. Um as far as micro
stimulation,
yeah. Um
under this picture if you activate those
neurons and you have a conscious
experience because of that it means the
the those microtubules got excited into
a state such that they a coherent state
such that when they collapsed you
experienced it. Um,
and I was going to relate that to
something else, but I forgot.
>> All All good. Um, maybe in sort of
close.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I I I remember. So, I'm
just going to relate that to how um in
the EEG binocular rivalry experiments I
I flashed up for a moment there that
sort of illustrated the moments of
conscious experience as moments of
synchronization across the brain. A
detail I didn't mention is that the
synchronization
at each moment incorporates
neurons that are representing what you
are perceiving at that moment. So if
you're at that moment you perceive a
house then your house area becomes
active at that moment and enters the
under the quantum picture enters the
coherent the entangled state or under
the classical picture or both pictures
it enters the synchronized state that is
the neural cororal consciousness as
already measured. Um, yeah. And when you
do it artificially, you're just inducing
the same state.
>> Neural coralate, neural causate. Who's
on first?
>> Neural substrate. I I prefer neural
substrate to neural cororalate.
>> Yeah. Well, in sort of closing, uh, what
are your empirical and theoretical
directions? What milestones or kind of
landmarks or reductions of uncertainty
could be ahead? How could people learn
about this area or get involved or just
take it from here?
>> Yeah. So, uh definitely needs more
testing. Um
and so avenues for testing,
one avenue that more people seems to me
should be trying is imitating the MRI
experiments of Kerkins and Perez. It
only it takes a regular scanner. you
just have to turn the dials in a
different way than you normally do. And
so you could try uh microtubial binding
drugs or other kinds of drugs to try and
um
isolate the molecular basis of that
entangled state that they appear to have
measured. Um, another experimental
avenue would be to try to do
spectroscopy experiments on living brain
tissue, which people have already done,
where you'd be looking for peaks that
correspond to microtubial resonances.
Um, and you would be looking to see them
either get reduced or shifted or
something under anesthesia or other
drugs that affect consciousness. that
although um people have done experiments
like that it will be technically
challenging because the signal I think
will be small in a large background
signal but that's a possible avenue. Um
I'm trying to replicate our rat results
in uh mice and we think we see that
happening in mice and this week I think
I saw it happening in tetraheim a
single-sellled swimmers which was quite
exciting.
Epic. Any last words?
Um
I hope that this uh hypothesis is starts
to be discussed more seriously by
serious mainstream re researchers now
especially since
the uh authors of active inference Carl
Fristen has written a paper saying
active inference must be quantum.
Yes, we had a 2023 course on physics as
information processing with Chris Fields
and have had a series of discussions on
some of those quantum active inference
and basing mechanics papers. Yeah,
there's there's so much there and how
exactly that
theory becomes
uh improved in its accessibility, rigor,
applicability, how the broader cultural
paradigm, etc., meta-cience environment
continues to evolve, all things of
interest.
>> Absolutely.
>> And I'll close with with with a
Blakeism. If the doors of perception
were cleansed, uh, if the doors of
perception were cleansed, everything
would appear as it is,
>> discreet.
>> Excellent. In the same poem, he said,
um, what is now proved was once only
imagined.
Amazing. Thank you, Mike. Good luck and
and hope people enjoyed that. Thank you.
Bye. Take care.
Thank you.